<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Gratitude | Feel Better Later</title>
	<atom:link href="http://feelbetterlater.com/category/gratitude/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/</link>
	<description>Act now. Feel Better.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 15:13:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>http://feelbetterlater.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-LightBlueFavicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Gratitude | Feel Better Later</title>
	<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Gratitude</title>
		<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/gratitude/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Clark, MD]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Baby Steps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gratitude]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://feelbetterlater.com/?p=526</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“The squeaky wheel gets the grease.” A true saying, but not always helpful. It’s important to recognize where things aren’t going well and apply deliberate pressure. At the same time, there is power in being able to recognize problems, set aside the ones that aren’t priorities to change, and find joy in the midst of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>“The squeaky wheel gets the grease.” A true saying, but not always helpful.</p>



<p>It’s important to recognize where things aren’t going well and apply deliberate pressure. At the same time, there is power in being able to recognize problems, set aside the ones that aren’t priorities to change, and find joy in the midst of broken systems.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Gratitude is recognizing the good things in your life&#8211;even if you feel overwhelmed. It’s a deliberate practice: find one thing that is going well. Recognize it. Give thanks to those who contributed. Set aside the negative for a moment and focus on what is good. Repeat often.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Practicing gratitude won’t fix all your problems. But it might provide a little lift to your outlook. And ultimately, approaching problems with grace, gratitude, and generosity will do more for you than wallowing in anger at the things you cannot change.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
