<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Self-Disclosure | Feel Better Later</title>
	<atom:link href="http://feelbetterlater.com/category/self-disclosure/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/</link>
	<description>Act now. Feel Better.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 18:40:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>http://feelbetterlater.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-LightBlueFavicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Self-Disclosure | Feel Better Later</title>
	<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>When you don&#8217;t get what you want</title>
		<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/when-you-dont-get-what-you-want/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Clark, MD]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Goals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Disclosure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vision]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://feelbetterlater.com/?p=482</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I had a minor setback this week. I applied for a competitive virtual reality training program and I wasn’t accepted. I had worked hard on the application, but it wasn’t enough. Setting aside the very real emotions of failure&#8211;something I allowed myself to feel deeply&#8211;what can I do next? Before talking about what I’m planning [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I had a minor setback this week. I applied for a competitive virtual reality training program and I wasn’t accepted. I had worked hard on the application, but it wasn’t enough. Setting aside the very real emotions of failure&#8211;something I allowed myself to feel deeply&#8211;what can I do next?</p>



<p>Before talking about what I’m planning to do, I’d like to discuss goals more broadly. Most goals fall into two different categories: <em>outcome goals </em>and <em>process goals</em>.</p>



<p>Outcome goals have a clearly defined final outcome. Lose 5 pounds Get a promotion. Save $1,000. If we can state how things will look at the end, we’ve created an outcome goal.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Process goals describe a change in ongoing behavior. Run for 10 minutes each day. Complete one extra task this week. Pack a lunch instead of eating out. Process goals are initiated and sustained; they are never completed.</p>



<p>A good process goal is usually tied to an outcome goal. “I will start running 10 minutes each day as part of my goal to lose 5 lbs.” “I will complete one extra task each day at work so that I’m more likely to be promoted.” “I will pack a lunch instead of eating out to help me save $1,000.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Process goals help us focus on what we can change, while outcome goals often have elements that are outside our control. We have a lot of control over whether we start running, but less control of our metabolisms. We can choose to work harder, but we can’t control whether our bosses choose to promote us. We can pack a lunch to save money, but we can’t predict whether we’ll have unexpected purchases or be the victim of a tanking economy.</p>



<p>When we fail to achieve outcome goals, we need to ask a few questions: did I do everything in my control? Can I try again, or do I need to do something different? What will I change next time? Is this the outcome what I really want, or is there some other way to reach my goal? If this outcome was dependent on someone else, are they willing to give me a second chance? We ask ourselves these questions with both compassion and honesty. Beating ourselves up doesn’t work, and ignoring our mistakes prevents us from learning. We often do the best we can with the skills, motivation, and situation we had, and <em>(not but!)</em> we can still learn to do better.</p>



<p>My failure this week was an outcome failure, so I’ll go through these questions:</p>



<ul><li>Did I do everything in my control? With the skills and time frame I had to apply, I did all that I could. That doesn’t mean that everything I did was perfect, but I did put forth a good faith effort.&nbsp;</li><li>Can I try again, or do I need to do something different? I can’t try again with this specific program for a whole year. To reach my ultimate goal, I think I’ll be better off if I do something different rather than waiting for this particular gatekeeper to choose me.&nbsp;</li><li>What will I change next time? The next time I apply for something like this, I’ll be sure to focus on conveying information visually. My application was primarily written content, and I don’t think I played to all of my strengths.</li><li>Is this the outcome that I really want, or is there some other way to reach my goal? I want to build meaningful psychotherapy apps in virtual reality. This training program is one way to get there, but it isn’t the only way. There are many other resources I can use.</li><li>If this outcome was dependent on someone else, are they willing to give me a second chance? Yes, but it may not matter by then. There are other ways to reach my goal. (And of course, failure to have my application chosen isn’t a reflection on me. My work wasn’t good enough for the competition judges. That’s something I can change.)</li></ul>



<p>In short, failing to achieve an outcome goal leaves us with two good options: improve our process so that we’re more likely to achieve our goal the next time, or adjust our aim with the new information we’ve just discovered.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Next week, I’ll talk about what happens when we fail to develop or maintain process goals.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is your vision for today?</title>
		<link>http://feelbetterlater.com/what-is-your-vision-for-today/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Clark, MD]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Goals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Disclosure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vision]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://feelbetterlater.com/?p=445</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last week I wrote about goals. I emphasized that even if you are skeptical about goal setting, you’ll be worse off if you choose the alternative: living life without any goals. Occasionally, people are ready to set goals without further thought. But most of the time, it helps to take a step back and ask [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="http://feelbetterlater.com/choosing-to-have-goals/">Last week I wrote about goals</a>. I emphasized that even if you are skeptical about goal setting, you’ll be worse off if you choose the alternative: living life without any goals.</p>



<p>Occasionally, people are ready to set goals without further thought. But most of the time, it helps to take a step back and ask where you see yourself going. A goal without vision isn’t worth chasing. You can get better at anything, but if it doesn’t matter, what’s the point?</p>



<p>So before you start setting goals, ask yourself a much harder question: <em>what do I want from my life?</em></p>



<p>You don’t need a complete life blueprint to develop a vision. Trying to answer a few simple questions can be a great start. What kind of work would you like to be doing? What would you like to see in a healthy relationship? Who do you respect and admire? What kind of exercise have you found enjoyable in the past? These questions can help you develop a vision that you can work towards. Don’t be too specific, and don’t plan any actions. There may be many ways to get there.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For instance, my vision is to <em>make mental health more accessible</em>. It’s taken me a long time to say it so simply, and yet I know that I’ll refine and change it in the future. It’s not the only vision I have for my life. But when I’m trying to find motivation to set and achieve goals, this vision absolutely informs what I do.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Regardless of where you are&#8211;start imagining a vision for yourself. This is a task that only you can do. Start with your feelings. Ask yourself what you really want. Be practical, but don’t rule out long shots. Build on your strengths. Use reason to clarify your ideas, but be generous to yourself. Don’t be overly realistic, because realism can’t predict all futures. Don’t live in fantasy, because fantasy alone can’t pay the bills. Share what you hope for with trusted, encouraging friends. Listen to honest feedback. Discard thoughtless skepticism. Choose a vision for today, even if it might change tomorrow. Learn from the changes. Above all, be compassionate with yourself; how else can you grow?</p>



<p>When you’ve chosen a vision for today, write it down. Knowing what you want is an incredible gift. Treat it with the gratitude and respect it deserves. Your life won’t instantly align itself with your vision, but with time, patience, and practice, you’ll get there.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
